JAILSON EDUARDO ÉVORA

Own Blog, LinkedIn

Software Engineer with a master's degree in Computer Software Engineering, experience implementing large backend systems in Net(5) and Java(8), including two as a lead; led the designs and integration of new APIs used by different criminal institutions in real-time, reducing the gap in sharing information from days to minutes; led re-architecture of critical part of system that serves entire court systems.

SKILLS

- **Senior development** skills include Microservices (5), SOA (5), SOAP Services (5), Design Patterns (4), Software architecture principles (SOLID or ACID over BASE) (4), Software Design (Composition over inheritance) (4) and designing unit tests to measure the effectiveness of software;
- Enterprise Framework include .Net (5), Spring boot (2), Hibernate (4), JPA (4) Entity Framework (5);
- Programing language like OOP Java (8), C# (5) and Functional programming like Python (6) and Scala (1);
- DBMS since SQL Server (6), MySQL (8) to PostgreSQL (2);
- Event-Driven for enterprise software RabbitMQ (3) or Stream Processing for internet companies Kafka(2);
- Language, English-fluent; Portuguese-native; Spanish-conversational;

WORK EXPERIENCE

2019-Present

DZone Independent Contributor and DZoneCore Community Member

- Contributor in Software Engineering articles with focuses in Java, Microservices, System Under Test, Spring Boot and security in frameworks;
- Over 60k articles views in 3 months and many acclaims;
- 3 published <u>articles</u>.

2018-Present

State-Owned Institution, Court Information System R&D Team, Lead Software Engineer

- Led the designs and integrations to external applications that allowed the court information systems to receive reports from different criminal institutions in real-time reducing the gap from days to minutes;
- Led the improvements and bug fixes that allowed for a more robust and stable system, leading to a 65% reduction in support calls;
- Led the review and implementation of workflows in accordance with new constitutional changes;
- Led the implementation of the incident management system that allows users to insert tickets and requests to the R&D and Helpdesk team.

2014-2018

State-Owned Institution, Court Information System R&D Team, Software Engineer Dotnet

- Developed WCF SOAP services that allow integration with many different external applications;
- Assembled a small in house data center for development purpose, including TFS source control and a large number of VM to execute night build and test validation that allow a reduction of 80% of the time consuming for the system under test (SUT);
- Implemented the authentication and signing mechanism with digital certificates, allowing security and non-repudiation of actions in the system.

2017-2018

National Institute of Statistics, Angola, Java Software Engineer

As Individual contributor:

- Initiated the design and architecture of a system to coordinate and harmonize economic information relating to enterprises, establishments, and groups of entities in Angola;
- Determining the usage of Spring Boot to build the Microservices that arranged the application as a collection of loosely coupled services allowing a number of benefits since

enables the continuous delivery and deployment of large, complex applications, improved fault isolation and eliminates any long-term commitment to a technology stack;

• Fixed the communication between modules using a publish-subscribe context, with Apache Kafka as a message system. Asynchronous messaging is fundamentally a pragmatic reaction to the problems of distributed systems. Sending a message does not require both systems to be up and ready at the same time.

2014-2017

Institute of Electronics and Telematics Engineering of Aveiro, Research Software Engineer

- As <u>master's</u> thesis, He restructured the exiting workflow system that allowed the
 integration of new tools for the modeling and definition of business processes, as well as
 the integration of the new workflow engine in the face of the inability found in the
 framework previously used to support some intricate features of the system;
- Developed and managed foundation services closely with the architect in research and discover new technologies and new ways to improve the system with an emphasis on software quality processes and guarantee the execution of software architecture principles and design patterns;
- Provided operational support for kick-starting technical projects and validate technical solutions.

EDUCATION

Master's Degree, Computer Software Engineering,

2014-2017 University of Aveiro

Grade: 15

COURSES

2018	1) Specialization in Software Design and Architecture (by University of Alberta through
	Coursera)
	2) Test-Driven Development (by Microsoft Corporation through Microsoft Virtual Academy)
	3) Software Architecture (by University of Alberta through Coursera)
	4) Service-Oriented Architecture (by University of Alberta through Coursera)
	5) Design Patterns (by University of Alberta through Coursera)
	6) Object-Oriented Design (by University of Alberta through Coursera)
2017	7) <u>Implementing In-Memory SQL Database Objects</u> (by Microsoft Corporation through <u>Edx</u>)
	8) Managing SQL Database Transactions and Concurrency (by Microsoft Corp. through Edx)
	9) Object-Oriented Programming in C# (by Microsoft Corporation through Edx)
	10) Build Web APIs using ASP.NET (by Microsoft Corporation through Edx)
	11) Creating Programmatic SQL Database Objects (by Microsoft Corporation through Edx)
2013	12) Heterogeneous Parallel Programming (by U. Illinois at Urbana-Champaign thro. Coursera)
	· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·
	13) <u>C++ For C Programmers</u> Part <u>A&B</u> (by the University of California, Santa Cruz thro. <u>Coursera</u>)
	14) An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python Part 1&2 (Rice University, Coursera)
	15) Functional Programming Principles in Scala (by É. P. Fédérale de Lausanne thro. Coursera)

Articles

DZone: Microservices in Publish-Subscribe Communication Using Apache Kafka

DZone: Using Java @Annotations to Build Full Spring Boot REST API

DZone: WCF Transport Security with Certificate Authentication — Test Validation with MS Test V2

Master's thesis: Reengenharia dos Workflows do Sistema de Informação da Justiça de Cabo Verde

Undergraduate's thesis: <u>Desenvolvimento de um Modelo de Política de Segurança da Informação em</u> conformidade com a Gestão de Riscos